<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English Jeroboam, or, The Protestant reforming magistrate and what the Church of England may expect from such a one precisely characterized by a transformed church-warden at a vestry-consultation held upon the putting in execution the laws against seditious conventicles : being London's caveat in electing magistrates.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3094</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28613</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10700612</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10700612</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45515</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45515)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1402:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English Jeroboam, or, The Protestant reforming magistrate and what the Church of England may expect from such a one precisely characterized by a transformed church-warden at a vestry-consultation held upon the putting in execution the laws against seditious conventicles : being London's caveat in electing magistrates.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Davies,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conventicle act. --  1670.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45515:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45515:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Engliſh Jeroboam: OR, THE PROTESTANT <hi>Reforming Magiſtrate,</hi> And What the Church of England May Expect from ſuch a One. Preciſely Characterized by a Transformed Church-Warden, at a <hi>Veſtry-Conſultation,</hi> held upon the Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Execution the Laws againſt <hi>Seditious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles.</hi> Being <hi>London</hi>'s Caveat, in Electing Magiſtrates.</p>
            <q>Diruit aedificat mutat quadrata Rotundis.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Davies,</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> near <hi>Pate-Noſter-Row,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45515:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45515:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO ALL Engliſh Proteſtants, By what Names or Titles ſoever Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified and Diſtinguiſhed.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Qui Conſulta Patrum, qui Leges Jura<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Servantes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy (if Loyal) Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is Recorded by <hi>Knowls,</hi> in his <hi>Hiſtory of the Turkiſh Empire,</hi> That <hi>Uladiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> having made a Truce with <hi>Amurath the Second.</hi> (Sixth King of the <hi>Turks</hi>) Sealed and Sworn to him in the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in a little Time vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated his ſaid League, waged War againſt him, gave him Battail at <hi>Varna,</hi> and was like to rout him: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which Occaſion, and extream Danger, <hi>Amurath</hi> beholding the Picture of the <hi>Crucifix</hi> in the diſplayed Enſignes of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> pluckt the Writing out of his Boſome, wherein the late League was compriſed; and holding it in his Hands, with his Eyes lifted up to Heaven, ſaid; <hi>Behold thou Crucified</hi> Christ, <hi>this is the League, thy Chriſtians, in thy Name, made with me, which they have without any Cauſe violated. Now, if thou be a</hi> God, <hi>which they ſay thou art, and as we dream, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the Wrong now done unto thy Name and Me, and ſhew thy Power upon thy Perjurious People, who in their Deeds deny Thee their</hi> God. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the uttering of which Words, the Battail preſently turned, and thoſe Perjured Perſons (the Authors of the Breach of Oath) were ſlain, and the Army totally routed. An Example hugely applicable to our preſent <hi>Swearers,</hi> and <hi>Teſt-takers;</hi> and was it generally weighed, would awaken a great many of our pretended <hi>Proteſtant Chriſtians</hi> out of that <hi>Jeſuitical Lethargy,</hi> in which they miſerably indulge themſelves.</p>
            <p>There is no kind of Men (ſay one of their Late Saint ſhips) can be ſuch compleat and neat Knaves, as a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> and an Old (well-studied) Profeſſor of Religion: when once Mens Conſciences are defiled, and they begin to trade in the World with a Pretence, that 'tis for <hi>God,</hi> they are ſo cunning that no Bonds of Honesty and Faith can poſſibly hold them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oaths</hi> (the main Pillars of Humane Societies, the greateſt Determiners of Controverſies) are in theſe times ſo strangely violated, and moſt impudently prophaned, as if they were but Bugbears to fright Children into Obedience. Nay, to ſhew what great Children our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates are, or to expoſe them as ſuch, an <hi>Ecclairciſſement,</hi> or clearing of thoſe Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> to be taken by them at their entring into their Offices, is Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and laid down, according to Conſcience and Religion, how far they might take them <hi>Salva Conſcientia.</hi> But was <hi>Indignum patella Operculum,</hi> a Caſe not fitly made, and ſoon was <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Caſed. And certainly, that Religion muſt needs be degenerated and apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,
<pb facs="tcp:45515:3"/>which <hi>God</hi> in his Wrath has appointed (as an Engine) to break down theſe great Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks of the World, <hi>Oaths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solemn Oaths</hi> are able to hold moſt Men's Conſciences; but Men heightned by Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the Forms of the Spirit, doing things by immediate Direction from <hi>God,</hi> carrying a Glorious preſence of <hi>God</hi> before them, affirming that they are called by <hi>God</hi> to do ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Signal Work in the World; theſe can eaſily mount above the highest ſorts of <hi>Oaths,</hi> and trample them under Foot preſently. Such is the Caſe of our <hi>Reforming Jeroboam;</hi> The Religion Eſtabliſhed in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was too great an Obligation to them, to revere that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority by whoſe Laws it was firſt Eſtabliſht: It taught them too much the Sacred Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Loyalty</hi> to their Soveraign Prince; 'Twould be a ſnare to them to go to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to Worſhip, leſt it ſhould invite them to entertain Loyal Thoughts of re-acknowledging their firſt Lord. A couple of <hi>Calves</hi> nearer home, would ſerve for the Vulgar to Worſhip, and he no ſooner thought on't; but they were ſuch <hi>Calves</hi> as to accept the Offer, and Idolatrous <hi>Bethel</hi> and <hi>Dan,</hi> are as zealouſly followed, as <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the true place of Worſhip: and this <hi>Jeroboam</hi> did, notwithſtanding a Trible Obligation to the contrary, by Three ſeveral <hi>Oaths: 1.</hi> When he Swore <hi>Allegiance</hi> to his Prince, as a private Perſon. <hi>2.</hi> At his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into his Inferiour Office, as Ruler over a particular Part of the Royal Eſtate, the Houſe of <hi>Joſeph. 3.</hi> At his Coronation, as Supream Magiſtrate afterwards. And this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Sin ever after to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis the ſame with our modern Reformers: They cant as Religiouſly as Protestants take the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and as cunningly as <hi>Jeſuits</hi> evade their Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance. They can Swear not to alter or endeavour <hi>Directly or Indirectly the Alteration of the Government in Church and State;</hi> yet are ready to erect a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> before a Church, or pull a Temple down, to build a <hi>Bethel</hi> up. They can Swear to Diſcover, and to their Power diſſipate any <hi>Meeting</hi> or <hi>Conventicle,</hi> which ſhall be convened contrary to the Laws, and the Practice of the Church, and yet ſo treacherous are their Memories, that they forget it; and alas! through inadvertency, (or I know not what) were ſtrangely over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, and found Members of ſuch <hi>Meetings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports in his Life) uſed to ſay, <hi>That</hi> Athens <hi>ruled all Greece,</hi> He <hi>ruled all</hi> Athen's <hi>His</hi> Wife <hi>ruled him, and his</hi> young Child <hi>at home ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her:</hi> So may it be tartly (and truly) ſaid at this time; This <hi>City</hi> Rules all <hi>England, Magiſtrates</hi> Rules the <hi>City,</hi> the <hi>Wives</hi> Rule the <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> and the <hi>Lecturers</hi> Rule them.</p>
            <p>No ſooner doth <hi>Aaron</hi> bid the Women to bring their Jewels and Ear-rings of their Sons and Daughters, unto him ('tis no matter to ſay further; hold, <hi>Aaron,</hi> do not tell them, 'tis to make a <hi>Calf</hi>) but the Widows preſs to caſt in their Mites, the Married Wives their Wedding-Rings, the Zealous Virgins their whole Stock, to their Silver-Bodkins. Such In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence have theſe Architects of Sedition, to procure their Materials towards their <hi>Babel-building.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> tells us of a Speech; which <hi>Pontius Teleſinius</hi> uſed to a <hi>Roman Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral;</hi> who, when he ſaw him buſied in delivering <hi>Italy</hi> from Thieves and Robbers, told him, that he did well to ſcour the Country; but <hi>Italy</hi> would never want <hi>Wolves,</hi> ſo long as there was ſuch a Spacious Forreſt, as the Great City of <hi>Rome,</hi> to retire unto. The Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of which is ſo obvious, as need nothing to be added therein. Purge the <hi>Fountain,</hi> and the <hi>Streams</hi> will run clear.</p>
            <p>Such, in ſhort, is the Compoſition of the Times, wherein our <hi>Reformer</hi> has the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to appear on his Stage. A Time, that <hi>God</hi> Rains Snares upon the whole <hi>Land,</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Men to act little elſe but Obliquities, Illegalities, Abſurdities, and ſelf Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; a Time, wherein <hi>Satan</hi> hath ſet the <hi>Land</hi> on Fire, and like <hi>Nero,</hi> ſits on his Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, making Muſick with his Inſtruments; his Religiouſly prophane <hi>Lying Pamphletters,</hi> that every Man may dance Antique over his Brothers Head. It is a Proverb not to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, <hi>That he that danceth when the Devil Pipes, ſhall certainly break his Shins, if he hath not the luck to ſave them whole, by breaking his Neck.</hi> Wiſe Men will not Travel in a Night, when the Air is full of <hi>Ignes Fatui,</hi> nor a Sober Marriner hoyſe up all his Sails, when the Winds blow in all Quarters.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45515:3"/>
            <p>Gentlemen, Through all theſe Diſadvantages our <hi>Proteſtant Reformer</hi> ventures to appear, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping he ſhall find acceptance with ſome, though not with all, whoſe Intereſt it may be to reject him. But this he promiſes; That if his propoſed <hi>Church-Reformation</hi> be at all encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, he will venture next at the <hi>State.</hi> However, lest you ſhould queſtion his Perſon and Parts, I have ſent you by him, a friendly <hi>Character</hi> of him.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>HE is One, he knows not what Himſelf, if you ask him; but is, indeed, One of <hi>God's</hi> Judgements. He is the <hi>Epitome</hi> or <hi>Abridgement</hi> of the Age; in him the Age is ſeen; and without him, the Times are not. Obſerve him in his taking his Degrees; from his <hi>Shop</hi> to the Chair of <hi>Church-Guardian.</hi> Here he tells you lies by rote, and not minding, as the Phraſe to ſell in, and the Language he ſpent moſt of his Years to learn. He is an arrogant Commender of his own Wares; for what ſoever he ſhewes you, is the <hi>Beſt</hi> in the <hi>Towne,</hi> tho the <hi>Worſt</hi> in his <hi>Shop.</hi> He never ſpeaks ſo much Truth, as when he tells you, <hi>he would uſe you as his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> becauſe he would abuſe his Brother. His Religion is much in the nature of his Cuſtomers, and indeed the <hi>Pander</hi> to it; and, by a miſinterpreted Senſe of Scripture, makes a <hi>Gain of Godlineſs.</hi> Thus his Honeſty having gotten him a Name, the Pariſh thinks him able to carry a <hi>Conſtables Staff,</hi> and become a <hi>King's Officer.</hi> Under this Title he ſwells, and looks big; and invironed with a Guard of Halberts, ſitting in his Chair of State, a ſhop-ſtall, peremptorily examines Night-walkers. He is a Scare-Crow to all Ale-houſes, where he is a great Stickler in a Tumult of Quart-pots, and ventures his <hi>Head</hi> by his <hi>Place,</hi> which is broke many times, to keep the <hi>King's Peace.</hi> He is ſtrangely ſtartled at the appearing of an <hi>Informer,</hi> whom he is ready to ſecure, upon their preſenting a <hi>Conventicle-Warrant;</hi> but he is as ready to let it alone in <hi>God's</hi> Name, as he is to apprehend a Drunkard for not ſtanding in the King's Name: And Men eſteem him for this a Zealous Affectionate; but then do miſtake him, for he does it but to be eſteemed ſo. Thus he becomes a Man of Buſineſs; and, if you would find him now, it muſt be at ſome <hi>Coffee-Houſe,</hi> which is his <hi>Eares Brothel,</hi> which ſatisfies his Itch. His Company here, all Men without Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the Principall are Old Captains out of Service, diſcontented Officers, Men of long Rapiers; which, after all, turn Merchants, and traffick here for News. Some make it a Preface to their Dinner. Others make it their Ordinary, and board here very cheap. In fine, 'Tis the Rendezvous of Spitting, where men dialogue with their Noſes, and their Communication is Smoak. Here it is, you may find our <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> or <hi>Conſtable;</hi> where he gravely diſcourſes of the <hi>Government.</hi> He converſes with you, as if he was in <hi>Spain;</hi> for if you are inquiſitive, he fears you as the Inquiſition, and Suſpects your <hi>Queſtions</hi> for <hi>Examinations.</hi> He delivers you Common Matters with great Conjuration of Silence, and whiſpers you in the Ear, <hi>Acts of Parliament.</hi> He is one that lies kindly to you, and for good Faſhion-ſake, and 'tis diſcourteſie in you to belive him. His Words finely ſet together, equally ſerve all men, and equally to no purpoſe. He kiſſes your Hands, as he did the laſt he met, and is your Servant to be commanded; but you ſhall intreat of him Nothing. His Proffers are univerſall and generall, with Exceptions againſt all Particulars: He will do any thing for you; but if you urge him to <hi>This,</hi> he cannot; or to <hi>That,</hi> he is engaged; but he will do any thing. <hi>Promiſes</hi> he accounts but a king of mannerly Words; and in the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Manners, not to exact them; if you do, he wonders at your ill Breeding, that cannot diſtinguiſh between what is ſpoken, and what is meant. Publick Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he will not wrong with his Abſence, and is the beſt Witneſs of the <hi>Sheriffs Hoſpitality;</hi> where he talks Rebellion in a Bravery, and ſpeaks big from the Spirit of <hi>Sack.</hi> Religion being now much in Vogue, he becomes enamoured with the Church: His Devotion there, is much in the turning up his Eye, and turnes down the leaf in his <hi>Bible,</hi> when he hears named <hi>Chapter</hi> and <hi>verſe:</hi> When he comes home, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends
<pb facs="tcp:45515:4"/>the <hi>Sermon</hi> for the Scripture, and two Hours. He is ſo taken up with <hi>Faith</hi> that he has no room for <hi>Charity;</hi> and underſtands no <hi>Good Works,</hi> but what he has in his Shop. He Overflows ſo with the <hi>Bible,</hi> that he ſpills it one every occaſion; and will not cudgell his Boys, without <hi>Scripture.</hi> He is One, that thinks he performs all his Duty to <hi>God</hi> in Hearing, and ſhews the fruits of it in Talking. He is a main Derider to his Capacity, of thoſe that are not his Preachers; and cenſures all Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, but bad Ones. He accounts nothing Vices but Superſtition, and an Oath. He expounds the <hi>Prieſts of Baall,</hi> Reading Miniſters; and thinks the Salvation of the Pariſh, as deſperate as the <hi>Turks.</hi> But now by the Grace of <hi>God,</hi> and his ſuppoſed Sufficiency, the Pariſh thought him a fit Perſon to manage that great Office of <hi>Church Warden;</hi> wherein he employes his Zeal, for the Reformation of it, accord<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to the right Old Frame; Where I leave him; the <hi>Church</hi> into a <hi>Conventicle, Conformity</hi> into <hi>Non-conformity,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> into <hi>Deformity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45515:4"/>
            <head>THE Engliſh Jeroboam, &amp;c.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>THE <hi>Veſtry</hi> being fully Convened, and <hi>Liberty of Speech</hi> being the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoubted <hi>Priviledge</hi> of all <hi>Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,</hi> our <hi>Church-Warden</hi> or <hi>Reformer,</hi> with a ſerious compoſed Gravity, lays open the Preſent State of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the neceſſary Reſolution he had taken for Reforming it, in the following Emphatical <hi>Oration.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>IT was a <hi>Bleſſed Eaſter (Brethren,)</hi> that raiſed me up again to this <hi>Ponderous Service;</hi> and if any <hi>Feaſt</hi> be Worthy of Annual <hi>Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> my <hi>Vote</hi> is, That the <hi>Feaſt of Eaſter</hi> (though <hi>Moveable</hi>) ſhall ſtand faſt for ever. <hi>Antiquity</hi> tells me, That the Office <hi>Gardiani Eccleſiae,</hi> is an <hi>Office</hi> inſtituted and dignified by the <hi>Fundamental, Known, Common, and Statute Laws of this Kingdom;</hi> (as for the <hi>Civil and Canon Laws,</hi> I have held them <hi>execrable,</hi> ever ſince the <hi>High-Commiſſion</hi> departed with a <hi>Duck</hi> in the Mouth on't, and the Impoſition of the <hi>Sacred Solemn League and Covenant</hi>) and this <hi>Honour</hi> is not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon any, but ſuch as are <hi>Judicious</hi> and <hi>Fidele,</hi> and able to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy (<hi>Couragiouſly, Sincerely</hi> and <hi>Conſcientiouſly</hi>) the <hi>Common Stock of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and Diſcretion belonging to the Pariſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not, I conceive, yet out of <hi>Your Memory,</hi> how <hi>accurately</hi> I hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſteer'd the Affairs of <hi>Parochial Government;</hi> nor out of <hi>Mine,</hi> with what <hi>Alacrity</hi> you ſubmitted to it. My <hi>Deportment</hi> then (correſpondent to <hi>Thoſe Times</hi>) was a fair <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>Square</hi> Dealing; and was, I preſume, a prime Motive to your <hi>Thundring Acclamations,</hi> in <hi>re-electing</hi> me the <hi>Principal Reformado</hi> of this <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Policy.</hi> In the exact <hi>Execution</hi> whereof, I intend with the Aſſiſtance of my younger <hi>Brother,</hi> (whom I ſhall well Educate for the Next Year) to uſe ſuch <hi>Preciſe</hi> Diligence, as may <hi>caſhiere</hi> many <hi>Fears and Jealouſies,</hi> and ſettle many things (hitherto <hi>incompoſed</hi>) in ſuch a graceful <hi>Poſture,</hi> that the <hi>Truſt</hi> of you, that confide in me, ſhall not in the leaſt <hi>Scruple</hi> be abuſed. But you muſt remember the Old Word, <hi>Diſtingue Tempora;</hi> and then (regarding the <hi>Turning round</hi> of the <hi>Times</hi>), you will conceive, that the <hi>Wind</hi> ſits in another <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;</hi> and I muſt <hi>move</hi> by other <hi>Rules,</hi> than formerly: for I am now more <hi>Spiritually Illuminated,</hi> and poſſeſt with <hi>Sounder Principles.</hi> The <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil-Law</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45515:5"/>is diſregarded, and its <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> ſtoutly <hi>diſputed,</hi> by our <hi>Goliah</hi> from <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> ſo that we ſhall ſee the <hi>Canons</hi> (<hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi>) <hi>recoil on the Canoniers;</hi> the numerous <hi>Army of Articles</hi> routed; the <hi>Oath ex Officio</hi> put out of Office; and the <hi>bottomleſs &amp;c Oath</hi> is ſwallowed up. The <hi>Caſe</hi> thus ſtanding, and that you may have a right <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of your <hi>Moderator,</hi> take an <hi>Epitome</hi> of my <hi>Reſolution;</hi> but withall, take this <hi>four-fold Advertiſement along</hi> with you.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>That I will follow the preſent</hi> Faſhion <hi>ſo far in my</hi> Diſcourſe, <hi>as to keep</hi> No Order.</item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>That my</hi> Interſperſion <hi>of</hi> Latine, <hi>ſhall no way Authorize the uſe of that</hi> Beaſtial Language in the Pulpit.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>That if my</hi> Phraſe tranſcend <hi>your</hi> plumbeous Capacity, <hi>esteem it the Fruit of my</hi> Liberal Education, <hi>before I ever hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the</hi> Sheers, <hi>or finger'd the</hi> Thimble.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, <hi>That you, who</hi> (<hi>for ſolid</hi> Edification) <hi>fall ſo nimbly to your</hi> Brachigraphy, <hi>ſhall not let this</hi> Oration <hi>paſs</hi> Grub-ſtreet, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my Approbation, <hi>nor (if it may be) until a Sweet</hi> Panegyrick <hi>of my Siſter</hi> Hannah's <hi>Compoſing, may be annext unto it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I begin with the <hi>Weather-cock;</hi> which is an <hi>imminent, gilded, hollow, craking, comb'd,</hi> and <hi>variable Creature;</hi> and doth ſo wonderfully <hi>Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize</hi> with me in All, and with the preſent <hi>Turning Times,</hi> in Some ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al reſpects, that I do <hi>Order</hi> it to <hi>Continue Statu quo prius;</hi> and the Four <hi>Fanes</hi> adorned with the <hi>initial</hi> Letters of my unſpotted <hi>Name,</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſedulous Attendants</hi> upon it in my Livery, to go which way ſoever it goes.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Weather-cock,</hi> I ſhould immediately have <hi>fallen</hi> upon the <hi>Leads,</hi> but an <hi>Iron Croſs</hi> hinders me in my way; which (with all other <hi>Croſſes moveable</hi>) ſhall be aboliſhed, that nothing may go <hi>Croſs</hi> in our <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Leads</hi> I find <hi>Prophaned</hi> with the <hi>Images</hi> of corrupt <hi>Hands,</hi> irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Feet,</hi> and with unſanctified <hi>Names;</hi> they ſhall therefore be <hi>Removed, Purified with Fire,</hi> and <hi>Converted</hi> into <hi>Bullets,</hi> to button the <hi>Boſomes</hi> of the <hi>Common Adverſary,</hi> and to ſeal up the <hi>Brazen Foreheads,</hi> of the <hi>Formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being <hi>Diſpatcht,</hi> I have made a fair <hi>Thorow-fair</hi> to the <hi>Bells,</hi> which indeed had been <hi>out of Frame</hi> long ſince, were it not that ſometimes they <hi>Ring the Changes</hi> (<hi>ſweetly conſenting</hi> therein with me,) and ſometimes <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciouſly proclaime</hi> an <hi>unknown Victory</hi> to the <hi>Over-credulous,</hi> or the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Coming</hi> of the <hi>Tories Alumna,</hi> and the like; which inflames all their <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Faggots</hi> in an inſtant. There is an <hi>Impeachment,</hi> as ſtronge as a three-fold <hi>Cord,</hi> againſt four of the <hi>Bells.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> They were <hi>Baptized</hi> before the Years of <hi>Diſcretion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Three times a Day they <hi>Pollute</hi> the Tune of the <hi>Fourth Pſalm.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They have <hi>Idolatrous Inſcriptions</hi> upon them; as (with a little of the <hi>Sexton's</hi> help) I have curiouſly diſcovered; For upon the <hi>Firſt Bell</hi> there is <hi>Peccatoris;</hi> on the Second, <hi>Mei;</hi> on the <hi>Third, Miſerere; Domine,</hi> on the <hi>Fourth.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Now, judge you, <hi>Brethren</hi> (who would ſeem, peradventure, to be as wiſe as your <hi>Officer in chief</hi>) is not <hi>Domine Miſerere mei peccatoris,</hi> noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45515:5"/>and groſs <hi>Idolatry?</hi> Are thoſe words fit to be uttered by a <hi>Profeſſor,</hi> unleſs it be with an <hi>Holy Deteſtation</hi> of ſuch <hi>Puddle?</hi> Ah! I ſee by the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout ſhaking</hi> of your Heads, that your <hi>Braines</hi> are troubled about it, that your <hi>Hearts abhor,</hi> and ake to think upon ſuch rotten <hi>Traſh.</hi> Well, it is high time, that theſe four be no longer <hi>Hanged,</hi> but <hi>Drawn and Quarter'd;</hi> that they, with the abominable <hi>Braſs</hi> upon the <hi>Monument</hi> of our <hi>Idolatrous Anceſtors</hi> (I paſs not tho an Old Aunt of mine lies mouldring under one of them) may <hi>concurr</hi> for the making of <hi>Ordinance,</hi> to batter down the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their <hi>Donors.</hi> The <hi>Wheels</hi> (being but <hi>Hemicircular</hi>) ſhall hang there like <hi>Meteors</hi> between Heaven and Earth; but the <hi>Ropes</hi> may ſerve the next <hi>Seſſions,</hi> at the <hi>Wooden Tripode,</hi> a Mile out of the Town, for the uſe of thoſe that will not <hi>Stretch their Endeavours</hi> for <hi>Whiggiſm,</hi> or the <hi>Good Old Cauſe.</hi> The Liberties of the <hi>Dawes,</hi> (our <hi>Beloved Allies</hi>) will by this means, be inlarged; and we will further <hi>Confirm their Incorporation,</hi> that from time to time they may make ſuch <hi>Ordinances,</hi> as are <hi>Conſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>Priviledges</hi> of their <hi>Houſe,</hi> and conducible to the <hi>Bene eſse</hi> of their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth;</hi> keeping their Courts <hi>ad Libitum,</hi> in the <hi>upper Region</hi> of the <hi>Tower,</hi> as we do <hi>Here</hi> in the <hi>Veſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Clock</hi> and <hi>Dial,</hi> becauſe they go <hi>Round,</hi> ſhall take their uſual Courſe; only by a Pious Fraud, they ſhall go ſomewhat <hi>Earlier</hi> in the Morning, and <hi>Later</hi> at Night, than <hi>Truth</hi> would admit of; Only to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge my ſelf on <hi>Three crook-Legg'd</hi> Youths of mine, who had rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with a whole <hi>Briggade of Whiggs,</hi> than move a yards Length againſt a <hi>Tory:</hi> Rogues, as they are, were out all Night, making Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, and Drinking <hi>Hazza's</hi> to the <hi>Duke;</hi> but I'le warrant—</p>
            <p>I have dwelt ſomewhat long in the <hi>Steeple;</hi> Now we will come to <hi>Church;</hi> where in the Firſt Place, I ſee the <hi>Font</hi> taking up ſo much <hi>roome,</hi> that would be capable of <hi>two double Taffata Gowns;</hi> which, I confeſs, I ſhould not ſo ſtrictly have obſerved, had not the <hi>Diſcontented Yoke-Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows</hi> of my <hi>Dyer</hi> and <hi>Hot-Preſſer,</hi> which are <hi>Crowded up behind the Door,</hi> drawn me to it. Away with it; this <hi>Font</hi> is abominable, a <hi>Baſon</hi> will be more apt for the <hi>Service.</hi> And thoſe <hi>Lofty Pews,</hi> which are higher by the <hi>Head and Shoulders,</hi> than their <hi>Inferiors,</hi> ſhall be <hi>Circumcized,</hi> that our <hi>Grave Matrons,</hi> and <hi>Sweet Heavenly minded Siſters,</hi> (whoſe <hi>Posture,</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Faces <hi>Weſtward,</hi> is moſt <hi>Amiable</hi>) may have a more <hi>chearful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence</hi> upon Us their <hi>Governours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Pulpit</hi> (in reſpect of the <hi>Form</hi> of it, being almoſt <hi>Round</hi>) is <hi>Tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable;</hi> although my Neighbour <hi>Zachary</hi> the <hi>Cooper</hi> (a precious <hi>Veſſel</hi>) could <hi>faſhion</hi> out One more ſeemly, and to better purpoſe; but the <hi>Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of it ſhall ſuffer a <hi>Reformation,</hi> and at the <hi>Pariſh Charge</hi> it ſhall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured with a <hi>Subſtantial Padlock,</hi> leſt they, whom the meer Natural Man calls <hi>Profound, Pious, Loyal,</hi> and <hi>Orthodox Divines,</hi> ſhould ſawcily any longer <hi>intrude</hi> it. I can partly tell you the <hi>Poor Condition</hi> of thoſe <hi>ſilly Prieſts:</hi> As ſoon as they aſcend the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> they fall on their <hi>Knees</hi> for <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſiſtance,</hi> as if they could not be <hi>Cock-ſure</hi> of it at all times: Then they have a <hi>Premeditated Prayer,</hi> not much exceeding a quarter of an Hour, wherein they <hi>Petition</hi> for <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and <hi>Pray</hi> for <hi>Kings, Queens,</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> and ſuch like kind of <hi>People,</hi> (though they know them <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh,</hi> (as our ſo-much feared <hi>Succeſſor</hi> is;) and then <hi>ſupplicate Our Saviour
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45515:6"/>Chriſt</hi> for <hi>Choice Bleſſings</hi> upon <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> whom we have found (by the <hi>Spirit</hi> that we lead <hi>about us</hi>) to be <hi>ſtrongeſt Lambs of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi> After this <hi>Meſs,</hi> comes the <hi>Sermon;</hi> which is the greateſt part of a <hi>Weeks Study</hi> (Written perhaps over and over) yet may be delivered in <hi>an Hour.</hi> Their <hi>Concluſions,</hi> which we are neither <hi>able,</hi> nor <hi>willing</hi> to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, are confirmed by <hi>Scripture, Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon:</hi> They conſult with the <hi>Original Tongues,</hi> and ſuch Authors as are called <hi>Authentick</hi> and <hi>Claſſical,</hi> fetching their Water from the <hi>Primitive Spring,</hi> becauſe they (empty Casks) think they cannot have as <hi>pure</hi> nearer Home. So, by their great skill in <hi>Divinity,</hi> gracefully attended (forſooth) with Variety of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Learning,</hi> they will exhort us to <hi>Study to be Quiet, to Try the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> to be <hi>Charitable, Moderate, Obedient to the Higher Powers,</hi> and to do things <hi>According to Order;</hi> with a great deal of ſuch hungry <hi>thin Stuff.</hi> I have utterly done with Them and Theirs; and am heartily over-joyed, that I have ever thought of this <hi>Happy Padlock.</hi> But of this, more at large by and by in its due Place.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pulpit-Cloath</hi> was the <hi>Legacy</hi> of a <hi>Blind Zealot,</hi> as appears by that <hi>Jeſuitical Badge (J. H. S.)</hi> upon it; for, as ſome of Our Learned <hi>Profeſſors</hi> do conceive, <hi>J.</hi> Signifies <hi>Idolatry, H. Hereſy,</hi> and <hi>S. Superſtition.</hi> Oh, here's good Work! What but <hi>flat Popery</hi> can be expected from a <hi>Pulpit</hi> appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell do with ſuch a <hi>Livery?</hi> Theſe <hi>Letters of Gold</hi> ſhall be delivered to the <hi>Finer,</hi> to make <hi>Silver</hi> withall; and the <hi>Velvet</hi> (becauſe it deſerves a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Wardrobe,</hi> and the coſtly Infirmities of the <hi>Teſtator</hi> ſhould be <hi>hidden</hi> by our <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi>) ſhall be <hi>Converted</hi> into <hi>Window-Cuſhions,</hi> for my new <hi>Reformed Parlor;</hi> where I intend frequently to entertain thoſe <hi>Immaculate Aſſemblies,</hi> which the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate</hi> call <hi>Conventicles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Hour-Glaſs</hi> ſhall be turned out of Doors; for our <hi>Extemporary Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> may not keep time with <hi>Clock</hi> or <hi>Glaſs;</hi> and ſo, when they are out, (which is not very ſeldome) they can take <hi>leiſure</hi> to come in again: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, they that <hi>meaſure</hi> their <hi>Meditations</hi> by the Hour, are often <hi>gravelled,</hi> by complying with the <hi>Sand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Communion-Table</hi> hath ſince 1660, regained its <hi>Antient Name</hi> and <hi>Sire;</hi> and (had I my mind) our <hi>nimble joynted Maſs-Prieſts</hi> ſhall never be ſuffered to <hi>Offer</hi> or <hi>Cringe</hi> there any Longer. But I will be bold with the <hi>Round Pillars,</hi> that inviron it, (when the <hi>Leaprous Superſtition</hi> is ſcrapt off) to make an <hi>Impregnable Fence</hi> for my <hi>Hoſpitable Buttery.</hi> The <hi>Plate</hi> that is there ſo <hi>Decently</hi> placed, I know to what <hi>Furnace</hi> it might be <hi>conveyed,</hi> to what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Form converted,</hi> and by what Means <hi>Multiplied,</hi> and <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Secured:</hi> But there is ſuch a <hi>Noli me Tangere</hi> upon it, that I dare not finger the Twentieth Part of it. But as for the <hi>Velvet-Cloath,</hi> adorned with the <hi>Jeſuits Badge,</hi> and the <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Gold Embroidered Glory</hi> about it, I ſhall put to a more Sanctified <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> with the <hi>Pulpit-Cloath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Organs</hi> are of <hi>Levitical</hi> or <hi>Popiſh Inſtitution,</hi> and like the breath of a <hi>Baſilisk;</hi> they deter hence the <hi>Two prime Grandees of the Pariſh,</hi> (the moſt <hi>Celeſtial Almanack-Maker,</hi> and the <hi>Beſt Tempered Potter,</hi> that ever lived by <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi> They drown the <hi>Virgin-Melody</hi> of the <hi>Galleries,</hi> and <hi>Middle Alley,</hi> and againſt our Wills bring our <hi>Confuſed Notes into Order;</hi> Therefore though I adventure my <hi>Neck</hi> (as that <hi>Deſperado</hi> did in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter Cathedral,</hi> and his Predeceſſour at <hi>Cheap-ſide-Croſs</hi>) I will ſet them ſuch a <hi>flat,</hi> that ſhall lay them <hi>Breathleſs on the Pavement.</hi> This <hi>Romiſh
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45515:6"/>Merchandize</hi> will yield good <hi>Engliſh Coine</hi> at <hi>Pauls,</hi> or the next <hi>Cathedral</hi> that is not <hi>Bankrupt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Table of Degrees,</hi> Prohibited in <hi>Marriage,</hi> is obſolete, and ſo is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage it ſelf, as here it hath been uſed; for I ſee no ground to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: but when all things are <hi>Common</hi> (as they <hi>ought</hi> to be) a Man may Marry, <hi>whom, when,</hi> and <hi>how often,</hi> as he will. This is a very ſhort, but a ſweet and comfortable <hi>Doctrine</hi> to you, (my <hi>Dear</hi> and <hi>Attentive Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory</hi>) and ſo the ſudden <hi>pricking</hi> up of your <hi>Eares</hi> doth aſſure me.</p>
            <p>Let us now take a little <hi>ſurvey</hi> of our <hi>Church-Books:</hi> The <hi>Bible</hi> (which always comes firſt to my ſight and handling) hath a dangerous <hi>Apocryphal Obſtruction</hi> in the very <hi>Bowels</hi> of it, which is of a very <hi>Malignant Influence</hi> upon the whole <hi>Body.</hi> This is Compoſed of ſuch <hi>Hiſtories</hi> as bind not our <hi>Credence,</hi> and <hi>Morality</hi> which ſhall not be the <hi>Rule</hi> of our <hi>Practice;</hi> it muſt needs be preſently <hi>Expurged.</hi> Yea, the <hi>Canon</hi> it ſelf, in reſpect of <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> is not free from <hi>Infirmity</hi> (and indeed, it is no Marvail, ſince ſo many <hi>Mitred Heads</hi> had their <hi>Heads</hi> in the doing of it.) The <hi>Geneva Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> is far beyond it. But Old <hi>Hugh Broughton,</hi> if he might have been ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, had exceeded them both. A <hi>Learned Synod</hi> (and what d'ye think of another <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> without either <hi>Root</hi> or <hi>Branch</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy?</hi>) muſt be the only <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> that muſt cure this <hi>Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Errata</hi> of the <hi>Book of Common-Prayer</hi> (as ſome call it) or rather the <hi>Lethargy of the Church of England,</hi> were they expreſt at Large, would <hi>over-bulk</hi> the <hi>Bible:</hi> Yet the Ravenous <hi>Eſaus</hi> of the World, had rather loſe all their <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> (which are their <hi>Birth-right</hi>) than one <hi>Meſs</hi> of this <hi>Red</hi> and <hi>Black Pottage.</hi> I will not <hi>contaminate</hi> my <hi>Lipps,</hi> nor <hi>abuſe</hi> your <hi>chaſt Ears</hi> with ſo much as naming any <hi>Errors</hi> that are in it; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to <hi>Rabbi Lewis Hughes</hi> (the Glory of the laſt <hi>Brittiſh Druides</hi>) and divers others, who have already <hi>ſmitten</hi> this <hi>Belphegor</hi> under the <hi>Fifth Rib.</hi> It further behoves us, that the <hi>Singing-Pſalmes</hi> be reſcued from the Back of ſuch a <hi>Monſter,</hi> and from thoſe other <hi>Humane Inventions, Te Deum, Da Pacem Domine, &amp; Quicunque vult: But whoſoever will</hi> that any (but the 150. <hi>Pſalms</hi>) be <hi>continued,</hi> may do well, in my <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> to defend <hi>Robert Wiſedome's, Preſerve us Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is an Error in <hi>John Jewell</hi>'s <hi>Works,</hi> but it is an Error with a <hi>Witneſs;</hi> and although it be <hi>Palliated</hi> over <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> yet it is <hi>inſtar omnium errorum</hi> and hath in it the <hi>Spawn</hi> of all <hi>Abominations:</hi> It is beyond pitty, that ſuch a <hi>Gemme</hi> ſhould be <hi>defiled</hi> with ſo baſe a <hi>Cognizance; He was a Biſhop:</hi> The very word <hi>Biſhop,</hi> (I fear, I offend in naming it ſo often) imparts all the <hi>Miſchiefs,</hi> that are <hi>deſtructive</hi> to a <hi>Common Church</hi> or <hi>State.</hi> Your <hi>Holy Indignation (Brethren)</hi> is well <hi>expreſſed</hi> by the preſent <hi>Groanings</hi> of your <hi>Spirits; but be comforted;</hi> for theſe <hi>ſtall-fed Lordly Prelates</hi> muſt come to their <hi>Fatal Banquet. Eraſmus</hi> his <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> hath found the more Favour hitherto at my Hands, becauſe he ſometime wrote a <hi>Tract</hi> in the praiſe of <hi>Fooliſhneſs.</hi> But when I remember ſome <hi>Popiſh Paſſages</hi> in his <hi>Colloquies,</hi> which I read when I was at <hi>Merchant-Taylors-School,</hi> I cannot well <hi>reſent</hi> his <hi>Beſt Labours.</hi> The Book of <hi>Deus et Rex,</hi> is a Pamphlet quite out of my <hi>Books,</hi> meerly for the Oaths-ſake that is in it. Theſe <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> are <hi>binding Things;</hi> the <hi>Latter</hi> was impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, when I was a <hi>Novice;</hi> and it hath ſo hampered me theſe <hi>Three Years</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45515:7"/>laſt paſt, that I would fain (if poſſible) caſt off theſe <hi>Manacles;</hi> for it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf, to us <hi>Whiggs,</hi> to be ſo <hi>pinioned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Book of Thirty Nine Articles</hi> is in many things <hi>diametrically Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite</hi> to our <hi>Fundamental Principles;</hi> it muſt neceſſarily be withdrawn, or farewell our <hi>Diana</hi> for ever. All the aforenamed <hi>Corrupt Volumes</hi> ſhall be <hi>Tranſlated</hi> out of the <hi>Church,</hi> and all the <hi>Iſles</hi> thereof into <hi>Little Britain,</hi> or elſe into <hi>Smithfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have but one <hi>Manuſcript,</hi> (I mean, the <hi>Regiſter</hi>) and that muſt be <hi>Corrected;</hi> for the Names of all thoſe that are <hi>Croſt</hi> in their <hi>Baptiſme, Ring'd</hi> in their <hi>Marriage,</hi> or <hi>Pray'd over</hi> at their <hi>Burial,</hi> ſhall be <hi>cancelled.</hi> No <hi>Names</hi> henceforth ſhall be <hi>engroſt,</hi> unleſs they were firſt <hi>Regiſtred</hi> in <hi>Holy Writ:</hi> Nor will we keep a <hi>Record</hi> of the <hi>Names</hi> of <hi>Strange Preachers</hi> any more; for they may deliver <hi>Good Doctrine in the City,</hi> who never had <hi>Orders,</hi> or <hi>good Name in the Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Pariſh Caſh</hi> yet, is ready to my hand; and I will preſume to ſeize upon a <hi>fleece</hi> of it, to maintain at the <hi>Church Door a guard of Long-taild Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciferadoes;</hi> leſt the <hi>Conjuring Littany</hi> ſhould ruſh in upon the <hi>Fourth</hi> and <hi>Sixth</hi> day of the Week (heatheniſhly called <hi>Wedneſday</hi> &amp; <hi>Fryday</hi>) that <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> be not read againſt <hi>Pride, Vain Glory</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſy,</hi> &amp;c. And leſt the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonian Garment</hi> (the <hi>Surplice</hi>) be <hi>ſhoulder'd</hi> in amongſt us; for to Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of our <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> no <hi>Smock is more Odious, than that of the Whore of Rome;</hi> nor any <hi>Petitions</hi> more terrible, than thoſe that would <hi>oblitterate</hi> our <hi>Principal Character.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of our <hi>dim-ey'd Anceſtors</hi> could <hi>ſee</hi> unhappily, to make their <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity Legible</hi> upon the <hi>Church-Walls,</hi> by ſetting up the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Prayer,</hi> (as they termed it) which is too narrow a <hi>Directory,</hi> or <hi>Summary</hi> of our <hi>Petitions:</hi> The <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> which are not (I conceive) abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Obligatory</hi> now under the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and the <hi>Creed,</hi> which is not (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> nor am I bound to <hi>ſtand to't.</hi> Theſe ſhall, in <hi>Good Manners,</hi> give the Wall to <hi>Choicer Scriptures;</hi> and I will be the <hi>Master of the Sentences,</hi> to Select them.</p>
            <p>The taking down of <hi>Popiſh Pictures</hi> out of the Windows, and bringing them (by a <hi>Legal Tryal</hi>), to a Second <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> was a <hi>Laudable</hi> and <hi>Tranſparent Work</hi> of One of my <hi>Brother-Church-Wardens.</hi> I wonder ſome of our <hi>Zealous Predeceſſours,</hi> of the <hi>Late Times</hi> (I mean, Fifty) had not done it, and ſaved him that Labour: But, <hi>Nil ſimul inventum &amp; perfectum,</hi> Rome <hi>was not Built in one Day;</hi> nor could they be demoliſht all in one Year, nor Two Years, There are ſome pretty <hi>Scandalous Babies</hi> ſtill left in <hi>Eaſt-Windows</hi> of ſome Churches, with <hi>trim Coats</hi> on, and an <hi>Orient Luſtre</hi> about their <hi>Heads.</hi> I remember now, I asked our <hi>Sextons Grandam</hi> one Day, what they were; and eſpecially, One I took great notice of? She told me, it was our <hi>Bleſsed Lady;</hi> but truly, if ſhe were my <hi>Mother,</hi> and <hi>as high as Heaven,</hi> I will (as <hi>Duty</hi> binds me) make her <hi>kiſs her Mother Earth</hi> again. And the <hi>Angels</hi> on the Roof of the Church (though they coſt Five Shillings a piece the <hi>Gilding</hi>) ſhall have their <hi>Wings clipt,</hi> and fall down to <hi>ſalute her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeths Monument</hi> was put up when the <hi>Royal Government</hi> had <hi>fairer credit</hi> amongſt us, than now; and her <hi>Epitaph</hi> was one of my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>J</hi>'s beſt Poems, before he abjured the <hi>Univerſity,</hi> or had a thought of <hi>New-England.</hi> I have had no ſmall ſtruggling within me, about the <hi>Tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:45515:7"/>or <hi>Abolition</hi> of this <hi>Statue;</hi> and, at laſt, have reſolved it ſhall <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue;</hi> but with a <hi>Curtain</hi> to <hi>Vail</hi> it, that we may regard or diſregard it at our pleaſure. For methinks, in Forty Four Years Reign, ſhe might (if ſhe pleaſed) have baited <hi>the Beaſt of Rome,</hi> to better purpoſe, and wrought a more <hi>through Reformation;</hi> yet, (notwithſtanding Her Majeſties <hi>Omiſſions,</hi> of ſorrowful Memory) if her Succeſſour King <hi>James</hi> had not been too <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Learned,</hi> as well as too <hi>Peaceable,</hi> for our <hi>Generation,</hi> and his <hi>Divines</hi> too <hi>Sinewy</hi> for ours to graple with at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> we had finiſht that <hi>Work</hi> long ago. We ſhall never meet with ſuch an <hi>Opportunity</hi> to do, ſince Forty One, as <hi>Now. Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> can now be <hi>glibly</hi> ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed under the <hi>Mask</hi> of <hi>Religion and Liberties,</hi> which we may juſtify to be <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and to come from <hi>Rome,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Geneva;</hi> and while we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to thruſt out <hi>Popery,</hi> we may bring in <hi>Whiggiſme, alias,</hi> the <hi>True Proteſtant Presbyterian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Eſcutcheons</hi> that are quartered over our Heads in the Body of the Church, are <hi>Emblemes</hi> of thoſe <hi>Honours,</hi> which ſome of our Noble <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors</hi> purchaſed with the Hazard of their <hi>Blood,</hi> in <hi>Defence of Religion, known Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberty of the Subject.</hi> I will give them leave to be <hi>Hang'd.</hi> But when I take notice of the <hi>Royal Armes,</hi> and their <hi>Motto (Beati pacifici)</hi> I cannot, for the preſent, but entertain ſome <hi>Mutinous, Diſloyal, Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Thoughts,</hi> and a <hi>Furious Zeal</hi> would ſoon drive them into <hi>Action,</hi> were it not that <hi>Conſcience, Allegiance,</hi> and <hi>Honi Soit</hi> upon the <hi>Blue Garter,</hi> did <hi>countermand it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some Alterations would be of Poſtures and Names, as well as Things.</hi> For truly, I cannot with an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright Conſcience, condeſcend</hi> to <hi>Kneeling</hi> at the <hi>Sacrament:</hi> We are not required to be ſo <hi>Flexible</hi> in a <hi>Superſtitious Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> My Advice is, That we ſit <hi>Familiarly,</hi> (as we did in the Late <hi>Free Time</hi> of <hi>Liberty</hi>) or ſtand to't <hi>couragiouſly:</hi> Nor ought our <hi>Geſture</hi> to be the ſame now, at the <hi>Goſpel, Creed,</hi> or <hi>Glory be to the Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As it was in the Beginning.</hi> Theſe, and other like <hi>Geſticulations,</hi> came firſt into this Country, from the <hi>City which ſtands on Seven Hills;</hi> and thither (with all ſuch <hi>Baggage</hi>) let them <hi>trudge</hi> again.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Names,</hi> I ſee no Warrant, but under the <hi>Man of Sin's own Seal,</hi> that this Church ſhould be called St. <hi>Clement</hi>'s; nor indeed (as I have learn't ſince I was <hi>inlightned</hi>) that it ſhould be called a <hi>Church.</hi> We only can diſcern, who are <hi>Saints,</hi> who <hi>Reprobates;</hi> and it is not hard to find, who, and what this <hi>Clement</hi> was, and yet deal <hi>gently</hi> with him.</p>
            <p>But in this particular (my <hi>dear Brethren</hi>) we muſt have a <hi>Reformation,</hi> and Order the <hi>Pariſh Clerks</hi> to paſs it in their <hi>Weekly Bills,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Harlots</hi> who cry St. <hi>Thomas Onions</hi> (knowing ſuch <hi>Egyptian Roots</hi> cannot be <hi>Sanctified</hi>) ſhall be <hi>puniſh't;</hi> and this to be as <hi>Zealouſly</hi> done, as he that laſh't a <hi>Carr-man,</hi> for whiſtling the Tune of a <hi>Pſalm</hi> to his <hi>Horſe.</hi> The Law ſhall be the ſame concerning <hi>St. John</hi>'s <hi>Wort,</hi> and <hi>Carduus Benedictus.</hi> As for this <hi>Building,</hi> which (now lately again) we have ignorantly called a <hi>Church;</hi> it is, indeed, but an Old <hi>Pile of Stones;</hi> it was built at the <hi>Charge</hi> of thoſe, who vainly thought a <hi>Decent Barn</hi> or <hi>Stable</hi> too homely for a <hi>Chriſtian Synagogue,</hi> and was <hi>Conſecrated</hi> (ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving your Preſence) by ſome <hi>Old Prelate,</hi> as <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> as the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> The Verity of it is, We are the <hi>Church,</hi> and this <hi>Fabrick</hi> (till we are otherwiſe provided) is but a <hi>Meeting-place;</hi> where (to our Grief) there
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45515:8"/>is too often a <hi>Miſerable Mixture</hi> of the <hi>Prophane</hi> with the <hi>Godly.</hi> For Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs whereof, there is no other way, than (in a Tumultuous Faſhion) to repeat the <hi>Preſenting</hi> of <hi>Petitions</hi> for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Seſſion of a <hi>Godly, true Proteſtant Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I promiſed you even now ſomewhat of my <hi>Opinion</hi> (my <hi>Dearly Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi>) concerning the <hi>Reformation</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in its <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or <hi>Clergy:</hi> Now, give me leave (by your Patience) to deliver it unto you; which I will do with as good and pious an <hi>Emphaſis,</hi> as I can; who deſire to <hi>ſpend my ſelf,</hi> and <hi>be ſpent</hi> in the Service of <hi>God,</hi> my <hi>King</hi> and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the preſent <hi>Church-Government</hi> by <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> their <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, Commiſſaries, Deans, Arch-Deacons,</hi> and other <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> depending upon the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> is evil and juſtly offenſive, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome to the Kingdom, a great <hi>Impediment,</hi> (obſerve this, I ſay— mark—) a great <hi>Impediment</hi> to our <hi>Reformation,</hi> and the further Growth of our <hi>Religion,</hi> (if I may ſo ſay) and therefore to be taken away: For (I ſay <hi>For</hi>—here's the Reaſon) they have been, and are entruſted with the <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Proviſion</hi> of the <hi>Souls</hi> of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> to heed, feed, and watch over them; and, as <hi>Ambaſſadours,</hi> to attend their great <hi>Embaſſy</hi> from <hi>God</hi> to Man, for <hi>Reconciliation;</hi> and Preach, or cauſe to be Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by <hi>Able</hi> and <hi>Faithful Men,</hi> the Word of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Seaſon, and out of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> They have done juſt contrary, run counter to all This; and this by Two manner of ways: <hi>Firſt,</hi> They have neglected their Perſonal Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their <hi>Truſt:</hi> And, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Have committed (generally and moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) the weighty Matter to Men illiterate and inſufficient, <hi>Dumb Doggs,</hi> as the <hi>Scripture</hi> calls them; that cannot <hi>bark,</hi> but againſt our poor <hi>Shepherds,</hi> that would <hi>Feed</hi> (not <hi>Eat</hi>) up the <hi>Flock.</hi> Men <hi>quorum eſſe &amp; vivere, eſt eſſe &amp; bibere.</hi> Whoſe Tables are full of <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Strong Drink.</hi> Their Precept's <hi>iter Longam,</hi> their Example's <hi>iter Breve. Satanae Satellites, non Chriſti Sectatores, ſed Antichriſti Succeſſores.</hi> They are <hi>Branches</hi> of the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of <hi>Rome; Plants</hi> not planted by <hi>God</hi> our Heavenly Father. What Immenſe and Tranſcendent Goodneſs would it be of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> could but theſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> be Sequeſtered, Silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and Turned out: and our true <hi>Miniſters,</hi> true <hi>Shepherds,</hi> [that would not kill them that they <hi>Feed, eat the Fat,</hi> and <hi>Cloath</hi> themſelves with the <hi>Wool</hi>] placed in their Rooms. 'Tis true, there are ſome of theſe <hi>Church-Governours,</hi> that are <hi>Good Men</hi> and <hi>Learned;</hi> but then we find them too <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſanctified.</hi> Like <hi>Curio,</hi> they are <hi>ad Republicae perniciem facundi:</hi> Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Eloquent, but to the <hi>Deſtroying</hi> of our <hi>Common-Wealth.</hi> For my part, I ſhall endeavour to pray for a <hi>Through-perfect-Reformation</hi> in the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as well as in theſe <hi>Particulars</hi> I have before declared unto you. The <hi>Church</hi> is the <hi>Garden of God,</hi> and till theſe <hi>Weeds</hi> be pluck't up, <hi>God</hi> will not delight to walk therein. And therefore we muſt, without Fear of the Hand of <hi>Violence,</hi> of <hi>Pride,</hi> or <hi>Informer</hi>'s Malice, ſet Hand, heart, and Shoulder and All, for the perfect Cleanſing the <hi>Houſe of the Lord.</hi> In ſhort, (my <hi>Dearly Beloved</hi>) I ſhall give you a brief <hi>Epitome</hi> of what Meaſures we took in our <hi>Late</hi> (bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi>) <hi>Times,</hi> and finiſh't our Work in this Matter, and how <hi>We</hi> muſt work.</p>
            <p n="1">1. None ſhall Preach or Declare in his Sermon, <hi>That the</hi> Puritans, <hi>now called</hi> Whiggs, <hi>ſhould be Ejected out all Pariſhes, nay Societies, as being ever
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45515:8"/>the only Cauſe of all the Troubles and Diſturbances in this Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. No one ſhall Preach, <hi>That our late (nay, any other) Petitions to the</hi> King <hi>for a</hi> Parliament, <hi>were like</hi> Jeroboam's <hi>Petitions to</hi> Rehoboam; <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and not Petitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. No one ſhall Preach, <hi>That the late and preſent</hi> Reformers <hi>of the</hi> Church <hi>were, and are but</hi> Hypocrites: <hi>That an Evil Spirit did Then, and doth Now breath theſe Things into their Minds; a Devout Devil, pretending Care of</hi> God's Service: <hi>That all Their and Our goodly Pretences, are but Hypocritical, and the Mask of</hi> Vile Iniquity, <hi>and</hi> Holy Theft. <hi>And ſhall hold, That it is a thing ſenſeleſs, for</hi> Lay-men <hi>to have any</hi> Tythes, <hi>and that</hi> Tythes <hi>are</hi> Jure Divino; <hi>and that to Alienate the Lands of Cathedral Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to ſet up and maintain</hi> Preaching Miniſters, <hi>is to pervert the Will of the Dead that gave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. None ſhall declare his Wiſhes and Deſires in his Sermons, <hi>That E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil may befal thoſe that go about to take away Government by</hi> Biſhops, <hi>which has its Plat-form from Heaven:</hi> And holds, <hi>That the Government by</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prieſts <hi>and</hi> Deacons <hi>under the</hi> Goſpel, <hi>is from</hi> God; <hi>as under the</hi> Law, <hi>the Government of</hi> High-Prieſts, Prieſts <hi>and</hi> Levites. And that ſay, <hi>That he knows not from whence the</hi> Presbyterian-Government <hi>comes, but from</hi> Corah, Dathan <hi>and</hi> Abiram.</p>
            <p n="5">5. No one ſhall call thoſe <hi>Irreverent Puppies, that uſe not Superſtitious Bowing at the</hi> Altar, <hi>and the Name of</hi> JESUS; <hi>and if they will not how Here, will bow in Hell hereafter; and thoſe that teach us not to bow as need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, are Blind Guides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. None ſhall Preach, <hi>That they that go about to Change the Laws and Government of the Church and Ceremonies, would at laſt change the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. None ſhall Preach, <hi>That it is as Lawful for a Woman, if ſhe diſlike her Husband, to leave him, and take another; as for one to go out of his Pariſh, to hear another Miniſter: And that to go to another Church, is as the ſin of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft and Idolatry.</hi> And threfore,</p>
            <p n="8">8. None ſhall Declare againſt <hi>A Preaching Miniſtry, by affirming, That to Preach nothing but</hi> Scripture <hi>without</hi> Authority <hi>of the</hi> Fathers, <hi>was like the Devils Sheering of Hoggs; a great Cry, but a little Wool.</hi> Or <hi>uſe that vile Comparing of painful</hi> Miniſters <hi>to</hi> Pedlars <hi>and</hi> Ballad Singers, <hi>that have moſt Company; when rich Merchants have but few.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. None ſhall dare to gainſay or contradict <hi>Extempore Praying;</hi> and compare thoſe that uſe it, and enlarge themſelves therein with (im) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> to <hi>Baals Prieſts,</hi> who <hi>Thought to be heard for their much bawling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Tenents</hi> and <hi>Speeeches</hi> in <hi>Sermons,</hi> held &amp; preached by our late <hi>Miniſters,</hi> were ſeverely taken notice of, &amp; ſeverely reprehended by ſilencing ſuch deſtructive Perſons, and Sequeſtring and Plundering Them and Theirs: Nay, if we could not find them erring in their Words, we way-laid them in their Actions, and were ſoon ready to pick holes in their Coats. 'Twas eaſy enough to ſay, they were <hi>Popiſhly Affected, Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, Superſtitious Adorers</hi> at the <hi>Alter,</hi> or <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, Swearers, Whore-mongers, Adulterers, Ale-houſe haunters, Malignants, Enemies</hi> to the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and the like; and we did their Work. Out we turned them Head and Shoulders, Bag and Baggage, to ſhift for themſelves. And then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45515:9"/>all care was taken that fit Perſons of our own Select Fraternity enjoy'd the <hi>Benefice</hi> or <hi>Cure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Brethren, that is the way we muſt go, not dally with them, but handle them without Mittins. We muſt thwack their Caſſocks; and rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle their Jackets. We muſt ſtamp upon the Panch of their Villany, and ſqueeze out the Garbiſh of their Iniquity. And dare they reſent our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with unneceſſary Interrogatories and unwelcome Reaſonings, they ſhall have <hi>Rehoboams</hi> Anſwer, <hi>Our Fathers</hi> (the Biſhops) <hi>chaſtized you with Whipps, but we will Chaſtize you with Scorpions, &amp;c.</hi> For the ſame Power, which was lately reſident in an Arch-Biſhop, is inherent and of Divine Right in a Presbyter. Ay, if they repine and call our Proceedings <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> we muſt put our <hi>Vincent Skale-skie, Humphrey Bang-Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Curtiſs Claw-Clergy</hi> upon their Backs. That <hi>Speculum Crape-Gownorum</hi> was an excellent means to vilify their Doctrine and Parts; and then a Fig for their Perſons. Oh! 'Twas pitty, pitty—Heretofore, <hi>Brethren,</hi> we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by a better way, by a two fold Authority, we had 1. a <hi>Commiſſion from</hi> Sir <hi>Simon Synod</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and 2. <hi>Reſolves of the then Commons Diſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament,</hi> concerning all ſuch Miniſters, who ſhould directly or indirectly Preach or Pray againſt our Power or Proceedings: We took Cognizance of them, and deemed and adjudged them Delinquents, and within the reſpective Orders, Ordinances and Acts touching Sequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to their Eccleſiaſtical Benefices and Stipends: So that in a matter of Seven Years time, a General Bill of <hi>Mortality</hi> being drawn up of thoſe Miniſters who were defunct by reaſon of our Contagious Breath, the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal amounted to One Hundred and Fifteen, who were Sequeſtred, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of above Forty Doctors in Divinity; their Goods we Plundered, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out their Families. Reformation <hi>(Beloved)</hi> could not have been wrought, but by theſe means, they were rooted in, and ere we could plant good Seed, theſe Weeds muſt be pluckt up. And then we wiſely Ordered the <hi>Directory for Worſhip;</hi> Claſſical Presbyteries, and Congregational Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips; Then had we our faithful painful Miniſters, and ſuch as Preacht <hi>in Seaſon, and out of Seaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having propounded this excellent Method for Reformation of Church-Miniſters, I proceed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ingens Opus,</hi> and <hi>true Maſter-Piece</hi> of all, now calls aloud for your <hi>quickned Attention,</hi> inflamed <hi>Zeal,</hi> and well-ſetled <hi>Endeavours;</hi> I mean, the <hi>Diſcreet Election</hi> of an <hi>Able and ſincere Paſtor,</hi> whoſe <hi>Model</hi> I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived briefly thus.</p>
            <p>He muſt not <hi>proceed</hi> from <hi>Wales,</hi> or either of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities;</hi> for then we ſhall never underſtand him: Nor yet from <hi>Jericho,</hi> leſt the <hi>Gravity of his Beard</hi> give us cauſe to ſuſpect the Truth of his <hi>Enthuſiaſms</hi> and <hi>Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> But he ſhall be a <hi>ſmooth, ſweet young Man, well deſcended</hi> (not from <hi>Levi,</hi> but) from the <hi>Tribe of Gad,</hi> or <hi>Man-aſſes,</hi> and trained up in <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Geneva,</hi> the <hi>Iſle of Silly,</hi> or (if you pleaſe) in our <hi>own Neighbourhood,</hi> where we have good Choice of ſuch, whoſe <hi>Mechanick Profeſſions</hi> have left them to make the <hi>Pulpit</hi> (as others do their <hi>Swords</hi>) their <hi>quum nemini.</hi> —Here are <hi>Felt-Makers,</hi> that can <hi>roundly</hi> deal with the <hi>Blockheads,</hi> and <hi>Newtral Demi-caſters</hi> of the World. <hi>Coblers,</hi> who can give good <hi>Rules</hi> for <hi>upright Walking,</hi> and <hi>handle Scripture</hi> to a <hi>Briſtle: Coachmen,</hi> who know how to <hi>laſh</hi> the <hi>Beaſtly Enormities,</hi> and curb the <hi>Head-ſtrong Inſolencies</hi> of this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45515:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Bruitiſh Age; ſtoutly</hi> exhorting us to <hi>ſtand up for the Truth,</hi> leſt the <hi>Wheel of Deſtruction roundly over-run us.</hi> We have <hi>Weavers,</hi> that can ſweetly ly inform us of the <hi>Shittle-ſwiftneſs of the Time,</hi> and practically <hi>tread out the Viciſſitude</hi> of all <hi>Sublunary Things,</hi> till the <hi>Web</hi> of our Life be cut off. And here are <hi>Merchants</hi> of my <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> who can <hi>ſeparate</hi> the pieces of <hi>Damnation</hi> from thoſe of <hi>Salvation, meaſure</hi> out every Man's <hi>Portion,</hi> and <hi>cut</hi> it out by a <hi>Thread;</hi> Subſtantially <hi>preſſing</hi> their <hi>Points,</hi> till they have <hi>faſhionably finiſht up their Work,</hi> with a <hi>well-bottom'd Concluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of this <hi>Groſs Heap</hi> (wherewith we are ſo comfortably ſurrounded) we may <hi>pick</hi> ſuch a One, that with a <hi>Stentorian Voice</hi> (making more uſe of his <hi>Lungs</hi> and <hi>Noſe,</hi> than <hi>Nature</hi> requires) ſhall reprove our Sins in that <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>meaſure,</hi> as we would have him; Shall couragiouſly <hi>ſound</hi> an <hi>Alarum to Battail;</hi> ſhall tell us the <hi>Events of our Actions before they're be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun,</hi> by expounding <hi>Old Viſions</hi> and <hi>Prophecies,</hi> better than he that was in <hi>Pathmos:</hi> He ſhall not need to Travel for <hi>Orders</hi> to the <hi>Prelatical Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> He ſhall receive <hi>Orders</hi> from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi> I have drawn up ſome of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready for him, and by theſe you may judge of the <hi>Whole; Ex pede Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culem, ex ungue Leonem,</hi> as we uſe to ſay.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Habit</hi> ſhall be a <hi>High-crown'd Hat,</hi> or (to follow the preſent <hi>Mode,</hi> to avoid an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndecent Pointing</hi> at) a <hi>Low-crowned, narrow-brim Hat,</hi> a <hi>black Leather Callot-Cap,</hi> a <hi>ſad Medley-Cloak,</hi> and <hi>Jerkin</hi> of the ſame, <hi>Violet Hoſe,</hi> and <hi>Ruſſet ſtockings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Landreſs</hi> ſhall evidence his Hatred of <hi>White-Linnen,</hi> by his little <hi>Coller'd-Band;</hi> and his <hi>Barber</hi> ſhall ſo roundly <hi>indent</hi> his <hi>Head,</hi> that our <hi>Eyes</hi> may as well ſee his <hi>Ears,</hi> as our <hi>Ears</hi> hear his <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his <hi>Fathomleſs Prayers,</hi> he ſhall <hi>diſpence</hi> with the <hi>Third Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and take the <hi>Lord's Name in vain ex tempore,</hi> cutting out more <hi>Work</hi> for <hi>God</hi> in an Hour and an half, than a <hi>ſober Man</hi> can expect ever to be performed by <hi>Him</hi> that is <hi>Moſt Wiſe:</hi> And if at any time (forgetting him-ſelf) he Pray for the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Majeſty,</hi> it ſhall be with ſuch <hi>Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Dilemma's,</hi> that we can hardly diſtinguiſh it from <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Text</hi> muſt never be <hi>divided,</hi> (We ſhall make <hi>ſufficient Diviſions</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves) but he ſhall wander from it, as if it were not a <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Body;</hi> only in <hi>Caſe of pure Neceſſity,</hi> he may (for a <hi>Moment</hi>) make it a <hi>Place of Retreat,</hi> and then <hi>frisk</hi> abroad again.</p>
            <p>His <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> ſhall be free from all <hi>Liberal Arts and Sciences,</hi> his <hi>Converſation</hi> from all <hi>Humanity,</hi> and his <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> from all <hi>Figures,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Hyſteron</hi> and <hi>Proteron, Hyperbole, Tautalogia,</hi> and other <hi>Flowers</hi> of the like Scent and Colour.</p>
            <p>He ſhall uſe no <hi>Language,</hi> but his <hi>Mother-Tongue,</hi> and the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> (if he hath attained to it) making choice of his <hi>Authors</hi> accordingly; ſuch as <hi>Aben Ezra, Rabbi David Kimchi,</hi> and the reſt.</p>
            <p>He muſt abominate the <hi>Greek Fathers, Chryſoſtome, Baſil,</hi> and all the Bundle of ſuch <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwholſome Herbs:</hi> Alſo the <hi>Latines,</hi> whom the <hi>Pope-bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied Gray-beards</hi> of the <hi>Town</hi> call St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> &amp;c. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate School-men, as <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and our Deviliſh Learned Country-man, <hi>Alexander Halenſis,</hi> ſhall not come within the Sphere' of his <hi>Torrid Brain,</hi> leſt his <hi>Pia Mater</hi> be confounded with their ſubtle <hi>Diſtinctions;</hi> but, by ſpecial <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> he may (for <hi>Names-ſake</hi>) caſt an Eye ſometimes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45515:10"/>
               <hi>Scotus;</hi> and (when he hath Marryed a Sisſter) upon <hi>Cornelius a Lapide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Engliſh Authors</hi> ſhould be <hi>curiouſly cull'd</hi> alſo: He muſt not ſo much as name <hi>Whitgift, Boyes, Hooker, Stillingfleet;</hi> nor any of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Anti-Preſbyters</hi> or <hi>Conformiſts:</hi> But his <hi>Chief Guides</hi> ſhall be <hi>Knox, Browne, Barrow, Buchanan, Robinſon, Baxter,</hi> and (whom I had e'en for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got) that never ſufficiently honoured and admired <hi>Howes,</hi> (not the <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologer,</hi> but) one of our late and beſt <hi>Tranſlators.</hi> He was a Man, that feared not to come cloſe to the <hi>Heels of Truth:</hi> He was a <hi>Laborious Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer of ſtrong Points</hi> to the <hi>Laſt,</hi> and had always a <hi>Lift</hi> or two for the <hi>Back-ſlider:</hi> If any <hi>ſtood ſtubbornly</hi> on his <hi>Pantofles,</hi> he would <hi>work</hi> him as pliable as <hi>Wax:</hi> If there were a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in his <hi>Charge,</hi> both his <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Awl</hi> ſhould make up the <hi>Breach</hi> in a <hi>Zealous Contraction.</hi> He well obſerved the <hi>Foot-ſteps</hi> of his <hi>Auditory,</hi> and grafted much <hi>Goodneſs</hi> into thoſe, that had <hi>gone aſide; driving</hi> his <hi>Holy Inſtigations ſo home,</hi> that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they went, they were <hi>ſenſible</hi> of them: In a word, He was the <hi>Hammer of all Humane Learning,</hi> a moſt <hi>Induſtrious Converter of Soales;</hi> and, in a ſhort Space, did ſet forth more <hi>Works</hi> in <hi>Oxes-Hides,</hi> than old <hi>Toſtatus</hi> did in all his Life. Oh! —I can never mention his <hi>Name,</hi> nor viſit his <hi>Monument</hi> in <hi>Finſbury,</hi> but theſe <hi>Spiritual Pangs</hi> ſurprize me— <hi>Oh! —He is gone! He is gone!</hi> But there is ſtill <hi>Heavenly Comfort</hi> provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for Us, and our Poſterity, by the daily <hi>Preaching</hi> of his <hi>Learned Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors;</hi> and their <hi>Judicious</hi> and <hi>Pious Works,</hi> the great <hi>Artichects</hi> of the <hi>Partition-Wall:</hi> True <hi>Herods</hi> in their Conſciencious Obſervance of the <hi>Sacred Covenant,</hi> though 'twere to the utter <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of Themſelves and Others. And now heartily thanking you <hi>(Holy Brethren)</hi> for your preſent <hi>Patience,</hi> I will proceed where I left.</p>
            <p>When our Souls are bleſt with a <hi>Doctor</hi> of theſe, and the like rare <hi>Qualifications,</hi> the next conſiderable will be his <hi>Stipend,</hi> (for this <hi>Oxe</hi> will not be <hi>muzzled</hi>) which I conceive (under Favour) ſhould be the <hi>Ampler,</hi> in regard there will be little or no Uſe of him for <hi>Weddings, Churchings</hi> and <hi>Burials;</hi> which, in theſe our <hi>Purblind Times,</hi> yields the <hi>Incumbent</hi> (as the <hi>Lawyers</hi> call him) a Comfortable <hi>Revenue.</hi> I think well (with Submiſſion to your Judgments) that we advance him to <hi>Forty Marks per Annum;</hi> but with this <hi>Proviſo,</hi> that our <hi>Benevolent Siſters</hi> ſhall not be inhibited their <hi>Voluntary</hi> Contribution of <hi>Money</hi> (their good Husbands knowing nothing of it) and <hi>Plate,</hi> (if their Cupboards afford it) <hi>Linnen,</hi> and other <hi>Neceſſaries;</hi> which, I am confident, will amount to twice as much. This was the meer <hi>Motion</hi> of my <hi>Reverend Mother,</hi> and <hi>Dear Siſter:</hi> And truly, I judge too very well <hi>motion'd;</hi> for <hi>This,</hi> with the Charitable <hi>Collection</hi> from the <hi>Saints</hi> on Week-day's <hi>Lectures,</hi> (according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Inſtitution, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.) will be a very pretty <hi>Competency,</hi> and ſhall maintain his <hi>Dear Conſort,</hi> the <hi>Lady Preſbyter,</hi> as Modiſh as the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>Lady Biſhop</hi> of them all.</p>
            <p>And whereas we never continue long in any one <hi>Opinion,</hi> but <hi>ſeperate</hi> daily, from <hi>ſeperation</hi> to <hi>ſeperation;</hi> I hold it <hi>expedient,</hi> that once in every <hi>Fourteen Days,</hi> (which ſhall be the New and Full of the <hi>Moon,</hi> the true <hi>Moderatrix</hi> of our <hi>Brains</hi>) we have a <hi>Solemn Meeting</hi> in my <hi>Sanctified Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour;</hi> where our <hi>Prophet</hi> ſhall give us a <hi>Conciſe Exhortation</hi> of two Hours long, or ſuch a matter; and then we may Admoniſh him of ſuch things, as in the matter or manner of his former <hi>Labours,</hi> were not correſpondent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45515:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>to our <hi>Humours;</hi> and may direct him (for the future) how <hi>long,</hi> how <hi>broad,</hi> how <hi>high</hi> and how <hi>deep</hi> he ſhall teach us, how <hi>gently</hi> or <hi>tartly</hi> he ſhall handle our <hi>Sores,</hi> and when he ſhall <hi>reſtrain,</hi> when <hi>enlarge</hi> our <hi>Liberty.</hi> And then refreſhing our ſelves in a <hi>Chriſtian manner,</hi> with a chirping Cup of <hi>Canary,</hi> and ſuch good things as the Gentlewomen <hi>Priſcilla</hi> and <hi>Dorcas</hi> will miniſter to us (being <hi>Devoutly Conſecrated</hi> by a <hi>long winded Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) every one ſhall depart home with ſuch <hi>preciſe Heedfulneſs,</hi> as may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the <hi>ſcurrilous Tongues of the Malignant Tories;</hi> for I muſt tell you, we have a ſort of <hi>ſcoffing Iſhmaelites,</hi> that will undertake to ſee <hi>Sin,</hi> where <hi>God</hi> cannot, and with their <hi>black Mouths,</hi> will Perſecute the <hi>Meekeſt Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac</hi> upon Earth. Witneſs their ſtrict putting in Execution their <hi>Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to diſturb our <hi>Publick Meetings,</hi> and their ſcandalous ſtigmatizing us by their <hi>Popiſh Pamphlets;</hi> but I think we are <hi>pretty even</hi> with them in this <hi>laſt particular,</hi> though our <hi>Pockets</hi> ſometimes pay for it. Witneſs our dear <hi>Baldwin, Smith,</hi> and Beloved <hi>Janeway,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe with ſome other things (I know not well what) are the <hi>Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> of my Thoughts, leaving nothing material to the <hi>Care</hi> of my Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, but the <hi>Subverſion</hi> of the <hi>Croſs</hi>-Iſle, the <hi>demoliſhing</hi> of the <hi>Arches</hi> (if without danger it be <hi>feiſible</hi>) and the <hi>Turning</hi> of the <hi>Main ſtructure North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> (which now moſt <hi>offenſively</hi> ſtands <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi>) or taking it all aſunder for a purer <hi>Edification.</hi> However though we are now ſuch <hi>Beaſts</hi> to turn <hi>Stables</hi> into Churches, yet let us abhor <hi>turning Churches into Stables;</hi> we will rather chooſe the <hi>former.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now only remains that in a pretty <hi>Diminutive Vote,</hi> you pleaſe to give your <hi>Brotherly Aſſent</hi> unto the <hi>Premiſſes.</hi>—</p>
            <p>Never was <hi>Veſtry</hi> ſhaken with ſuch a <hi>Thunderclap!</hi> The Air ſeldome ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers ſuch a <hi>Holy Violence:</hi> Your loud Chriſtian <hi>Clamor</hi> brought this Earth into ſuch a fit of <hi>Trembling,</hi> that (I am partly perſwaded) the <hi>Graves</hi> were in ſome doubt they ſhould be diſpoſſeſt of their <hi>Gueſts:</hi> But I am ſure this <hi>Gale</hi> hath driven out <hi>Billowes</hi> of joyful <hi>Tears</hi> at my <hi>Eyes,</hi> and blown my <hi>Zeal</hi> into an <hi>extinguiſhable Conflagation,</hi> which had well nigh <hi>pufft</hi> me up into another <hi>Extaſy.</hi> This is <hi>Vis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> indeed, that can ſet all the <hi>Elements</hi> on Work thus at a <hi>Clap.</hi> Your unanimous Approbation (my <hi>Zealous Brethren</hi>) Obligeth my extreameſt <hi>Abilities</hi> to the <hi>Proſecution</hi> of my <hi>Intendments,</hi> reſolving as long as the Old Word <hi>(Magiſtratus indicat virum)</hi> ſtands firm, my <hi>Demeanor</hi> ſhall expreſs me to the Life, and make the <hi>Whigg</hi> as Famous to Poſterity, as the <hi>Roundhead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if the well tun'd <hi>Vox Populi</hi> of this Precinct ſhall Honour me to be your <hi>Common-Council-Man,</hi> my <hi>Learned Oratory</hi> in <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Devotion</hi> in the whole <hi>Service,</hi> ſhall render me as <hi>Pragmatical</hi> and <hi>Phanatical</hi> a Member in the <hi>Civil Government,</hi> as poſſibly I am or can be in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which you may expect ſhortly an Account.</p>
            <q>—Semel Inſanivimus Omnes.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
